<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Common-good: or, The improvement of commons, forrests, and chases, by inclosure. Wherein the advantage of the poor, the common plenty of all, and the increase and preservation of timber, with other things of common concernment, are considered. / By S.T.</title>
            <author>S. T. (Silvanus Taylor)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95596</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T552</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E663_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203768</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863594</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863594</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115804</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95596)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115804)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 102:E663[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Common-good: or, The improvement of commons, forrests, and chases, by inclosure. Wherein the advantage of the poor, the common plenty of all, and the increase and preservation of timber, with other things of common concernment, are considered. / By S.T.</title>
                  <author>S. T. (Silvanus Taylor)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Francis Tyton, and are to be sold at his shop at the sign of the three Daggers neer the Middle-Temple gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Silvanus Taylor.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May. 11".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Inclosures --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Poor --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:115804:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Common-Good: OR, THE IMPROVEMENT OF Commons, Forreſts, and Chaſes, BY INCLOSURE.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN The Advantage of the Poor, THE Common Plenty of All, AND The Increaſe and Preſervation of TIMBER, With other things of common concernment, Are Conſidered.</p>
            <p>By <hi>S. T.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Francis Tyton,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſign of the three Daggers neer the <hi>Middle-Temple</hi> gate, 1652.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:115804:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115804:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Supreme Authority OF THIS NATION THE <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> The onely proper Councellors for COMMON-GOOD.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>All Wiſdom, Peace, Honor, and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Happineſs,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is deſired (of that God, whoſe <hi>Spirit</hi> in a myſtery of Providence hath been eminently ſeen in you,)</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>BY An obſerving Honorer of
Your Faithfulneſs, <hi>Silvanus Taylor.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:115804:3"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>SEct.</hi> 1. In the which are ſet down the general Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt Incloſures of Commons, with brief An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers thereunto.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. In which is ſet forth the ſeveral ſorts of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. Wherein the Common-fields neer Towns and Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages are treated of.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. Of Commons in rich low Grounds.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. Of Commons which are plain Upland Grounds.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 6. Of Commons which are apt for Wood, and over-ſpread with Buſhes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 7. Of Commons cumbred with Bryars, Thorns, Heath, Moſs, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 8. Which treateth of Forreſts and Chaſes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 9. Of the way and manner of incloſing Commons.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 10. Treating of the manner of incloſing Forrests and Chaſes, with ſome brief directions for planting and preſerving Wood; that ſo it may be a proviſion for our Navy to all generations.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:115804:3"/>
            <head>Common-Good: OR The Improvement of Commons, Forreſts, and Chaſes, by Incloſure.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I. <hi>In which are ſet down the general Exceptions againſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſures of Commons, with brief Anſwers thereunto.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is believed, that Commons are a ſixth part of the Land of <hi>England,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing common to many conſequentials, there's no perſonal propriety, the chief reaſon that they continue ſtill over-run with a Curſe.</p>
               <p>It is natural for all men to love propriety; the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, becauſe conveniency is it's adjunct, and men do delight rather to ſay <hi>this is mine,</hi> then <hi>this is ours;</hi> for the one, he holds but in Common a notion of extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation to love, the other he is ſole Lord of, and ſo hath it at his own diſpoſing. Mans Will (as corrupted) would be lord paramount, and had it but wings and ſtrength, would quickly ſurmount the whole Univerſe,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115804:4"/>
and be (as our deſire is) as Gods. It was once <hi>Adams</hi> happineſs (even in the ſtate of innocency) to dreſs the Garden, and eat of the fruit thereof, but it was his great unhappineſs to be thruſt out into the large field of the World: in the one were all things delightful, the other had the curſe; <hi>Bryars and Thorns ſhalt thou bring forth:</hi> Did that curſe terminate in the perſon of <hi>Adam?</hi> Surely no; for the ſame God ſaith now to the ſons of <hi>Adam, He that will not work, let him not eat.</hi> The <hi>Turks</hi> will tell you, <hi>the bread of Idleneſs is no mans.</hi> What's the matter with us in <hi>England,</hi> that we labor not to remove the curſe, and reduce thoſe large briary and thorny Commons (who offer themſelves) if not into a Paradiſe, yet into pleaſant Gardens, fruitful Orchards, goodly fields of Corn, feeding paſtures for all ſorts of Cattel, ſtately Woods, and pleaſing Groves? All which, with reaſonable labor, would be obtained. But is there not a worſe curſe befaln <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, even the curſe of blinde ignorance? that we cannot ſee nor know the great good that would redound to this our <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> by the Incloſing of thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny large, yet little profitable Commons amongſt us, that ſtill lie under the curſe; and therefore many op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the good, and like drunken men, labor more to be ſick, then ſober men do to keep themſelves in health. If you continue to be deceived, yet it ſhall be my work, and truly I think it my duty, to employ my poor Talent for my Countries good (though I bring but a little Goats hair) to undeceive thoſe, that either by their own weakneſs, or others deluſions, are ſtill kept in the dark. Therefore the Method that I ſhall uſe, will be,</p>
               <p>Firſt, to ſet down the general Objections againſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115804:4"/>
Incloſing, and then to give ſome brief Anſwers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I ſhal ſhew the ſeveral Natures of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in <hi>England,</hi> and how they are more or leſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious by incloſing.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, and laſtly, I ſhall treat of the way and manner of Incloſing.</p>
               <div type="objections_and_answers">
                  <head>The Objections are theſe:</head>
                  <p>1 <hi>Object.</hi> The firſt Objection is, <hi>That the Incloſures of Commons is the undoing of many poor, who have their onely livelyhood out of them; for that a poor man, having a wife and many children, by a cottage and Common, hath the benefit of a Cows going, and the keeping of ſheep, and of getting buſhes for his fuel: And Experience tells us, that thoſe, who have incloſed, and thruſt out the poor, have received proportionable to their demerits; for the Curſe of the poor hath lighted on them, or their Families.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2 Object. <hi>That if Commons are incloſed, it will much decreaſe ſheep, and conſequently Wool and Manufactory, by which the hands of many poor are employed, and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants enriched by tranſporting our Cloth into many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote parts of the World; for there will be ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to tillage and paſturage for other cattel, that little will be left for ſheep.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>3 <hi>Object.</hi> The third Objection is, <hi>That the Free and Copy-Holders have now the benefit of Commons, which if incloſed, the Lord will have a third part; ſo that thereby many will be made poor, for the enriching of one, againſt the nature of a Commonwealth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To the firſt Objection, where it is ſaid, <hi>That incloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hath and will be the undoing of many poor, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwer, That did that poor man live in ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, where himſelf, his wife and children might
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115804:5"/>
be employed in ſome manufactory, or they betake themſelves to the ſpinning of Worſted, Woolen, Flax, or ſuch like eaſie works (which a childe of ſix years old may profitably be employed in) certainly it would be much more comfortable for them, and much better for the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> then if they (as uſually now they do) ſhould be Lazying upon a Common to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend one Cow, and a few ſheep, for we ſeldom ſee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny living on <hi>Commons</hi> ſet themſelves to a better em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment. And if the father do work ſometimes, and ſo get bread, yet the children are ſeldom brought up to any thing; but being nurſed up in idleneſs in their youth, they become indiſpoſed for labor, and then begging is their portion, or Theevery their Trade: ſo that though <hi>Commons</hi> be a help to one, yet it's a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine to many, which the Government of a Free State abhors, in that a common plenty and liberty (the greateſt advantages of ſociety) naturally conſerve it, as the contraries do a Monarchy, which at the beſt is beſt but for a few. And for that it is ſaid, <hi>the curſe of the poor hath lighted on the Incloſers of Commons, or their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies;</hi> I anſwer, That if the way hereafter propoſed for the incloſing of <hi>Commons</hi> be followed, the poor (as they will have no cauſe to curſe) will exceedingly bleſs God for the incloſing of them.</p>
                  <p>To the ſecond Objection, <hi>That incloſing of Common will much leſsen the breed of Sheep, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwer, That there are many grounds now in Commons ſo unkindly for Sheep (which the skilful Countryman obſerves, and is much diſcouraged to put ſheep thereon) which if incloſed, then would he ſo ſever his grounds, that he would put Cattel in each ground moſt agreeable to their nature; the dry
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115804:5"/>
Up-land grounds for ſheep, and the low wet grounds for his other Cattel; and this would be ſo far from leſſening the breed of ſheep, that it will much encreaſe them: for a good Husbandman will quickly find out what his Land his moſt fit for.</p>
                  <p>Again, <hi>Commons</hi> generally are over-grown with Heath, Moſs, Fearn or Brackin, Furzes or Gorſt, &amp;c. ſo that both ſheep and other Cattel muſt be ſtill pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to keep them alive: And it is ſeldom ſeen, that thoſe which are bred on <hi>Commons</hi> are of any great growth; but we finde by experience, that generally the improvement of one ſheep in paſture is more then of two that are kept on the <hi>Commons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is further ſaid and granted, <hi>That Wool is the great Staple Commodity of this Nation, and therefore ought chiefly to be preſerved.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I muſt acknowledg, that Wool is a clothing-bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this Nation, more then to any other, it being eminently uſeful for Manufactory, and that which Merchants trade with into many parts of the world, by which we at home are ſupplied with many convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. But obſerve, that the ſuper-abundance of that commodity of Wool we now ſpare, is often exchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for the ſupply of that which is of more abſolute neceſſity; as Corn, which by incloſing might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured at home. Wherefore judg, whether it be not much better to leſſen our Wool, and thereby have plenty of Corn and Cattel within our own Nation, then by ſelling our Wool to buy Corn in other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. For known to all, that Corn is of abſolute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, and therefore primarily to be intended, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the Spirit of life called <hi>the ſtaff of life,</hi> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the beſt concocted ſpirits, and moſt ſuitable to the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115804:6"/>
nature of man, it being of the immediate production of the Earth (as man was.) Our ancient and common Law, the very life (if actuated by the influence of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority) of <hi>Common-Good,</hi> well provided, that diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes on the Plough ſhould not be made; but ſo much cannot be ſaid of Wool, though it be of good and great uſe. And although our Merchants are an honor to our Nations in moſt parts of the World, and do bring home many neceſſary Commodities, yet ſtill it muſt give this honor, That Corn and Cattel are of moſt abſolute neceſſity: And that all forreign com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities and incommodities (as Wine, Silks, Spices, and Tobacco) are purchaſed with that which ariſeth out of our own Nation, as that chiefly of Wool, Fiſh, Tin, and Lead; all which (it's hoped) will be much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved to the increaſe of forraign Trade.</p>
                  <p>To the third Objection, <hi>That Free and Copy-Holders have more benefit by Commons now, then if incloſed, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwer, This benefit is not unto all that have a right to <hi>Common,</hi> but to ſome few that live neer upon the <hi>Common;</hi> for others, that live but half a mile from the <hi>Common,</hi> have but little benefit thereof: And un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Cattel, which are put thereon, be dayly looked unto, they oftentimes ſtray ſo far (if not loſt) that the time ſpent in looking after them, is more then the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the <hi>Commons</hi> comes to: And indeed thoſe that have the largeſt purſe, have the largeſt ſhare on the <hi>Commons;</hi> by which means there is a petty Tyranny exerciſed: ſo that this Myſtery of Oppreſſion ſhould be unravelled by the hand of <hi>Common-Good.</hi> And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly much better would it be for them to have two Acres incloſed, then to have a right to five Acres in <hi>Common,</hi> out of which cometh very little profit at preſent; and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115804:6"/>
ſo long as it is in <hi>Common,</hi> no hopes of improvement for the future: And therefore I deſire that the name of <hi>Commons</hi> at leaſt may be altered; for its denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is contrary to its nature, an old cloud genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to darken all that have not a Perſpective to look beyond Tradition.</p>
                  <p>By that little which hath been ſaid, it may be eaſily diſcerned, that the preſent benefits by <hi>Commons</hi> are not of ſuch great worth as many men would blow them up unto: And that, which will come far ſhort of the good which may redound unto the Publique-wealth, if incloſed in that manner hereafter pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II. <hi>In which is ſet forth the ſeveral Sorts of COMMONS.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>COmmons in <hi>England</hi> are of divers natures: As,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, <hi>Common-fields,</hi> which uſually are neer and about Towns or Villages, and ordinarily kept in Tillage.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond ſort of <hi>Commons</hi> are thoſe low grounds of Meadows or Mariſhes, that have the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of Rivers or Brooks, which overflowing them, make them fruitful, or otherwiſe of themſelves are naturally ſo.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A third ſort of <hi>Commons</hi> are thoſe that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called <hi>Downs,</hi> and are chiefly for the keeping of ſheep, being dry grounds, and not much cumbred with Buſhes, Furzes, Fearn, Heath, or Moſs.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:115804:7"/>
4. The fourth ſort are ſuch as are apt for Wood, and are over-run with buſhes, which are moſt fit for the breed of young Cattel and Horſes.</p>
               <p n="5">5. A fifth ſort are that which are over-ſpred with Furzes, Heath, and Moſs, being ſuch as moſt part of <hi>Wales</hi> doth abound with, and on which are Sheep and Cattel of all ſorts bred.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The ſixth ſort are thoſe of Forreſts and Chaſes, in which were great ſtore of Red and Fallow Deer preſerved, to the prejudice of the Inhabitants adjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>My endevor herein ſhall be to ſhew how each of theſe may be improved to each particular mans inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and ſo to the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> in general. I ſhall ſay but little to the three firſt of theſe, but ſhal chiefly inſiſt on the great improvement that may be made on the three laſt: And my aym therein is Plenty, one means of a flouriſhing <hi>Commonwealth:</hi> And yet I would as much as poſſible preſerve each mans particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar intereſt. And that which I lay down for a ground whereon I mean to build, and to have an eye unto throughout my Diſcourſe, ſhall be theſe three ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals:</p>
               <p>Firſt, The encreaſe of thoſe neceſſary Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which our Country doth naturally afford, and that chiefly Corn, Cattel, and Wood.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The encreaſe of Manufactory, and ſo conſequently of Trade.</p>
               <p>The third is, of Strength and Safety.</p>
               <p>All which, I doubt not, will finde acceptance with thoſe, whom God by his wiſe Providence hath now placed in Authority, for the good of the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:115804:7"/>
               <head>SECT. III. <hi>Wherein the Common-fields neer Towns and Villages are treated of.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr this firſt ſort of <hi>Commons,</hi> there is very little loſs to the Publique thereby, the Owners thereof being neceſſitated to keep them in Tillage.</p>
               <p>But yet if incloſed, I deſire it may be conſidered, if theſe benefits would not follow; as firſt, whether it would not be more profitable, if incloſed, and that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man had all his own ground at his own diſpoſing, to make choyce of thoſe grounds moſt fit for Corn, and them to employ with leſs labor, leſs coſt, and much more encreaſe: for oftentimes it is ſeen, that the <hi>Common-fields</hi> are very much impoveriſhed by continual plowing, eſpecially in light, ſandy, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velly grounds, or in any other light ground where the ſoyl is but ſhallow: And to ſuch Land there muſt be a continual help by ſome kinde of compaſs or other, elſe the Corn is thin and weak, and bears a ſmall hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-Bee-Ear with few grains therein; ſo that the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman hath very little encreaſe in ſuch <hi>Common-field ground.</hi> Beſides, ſuch light ground in wet years doth produce tares, and other weeds, very deſtructive to the Corn; all which would be avoyded, if the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman could make choyce of his ground to ſuch uſes as his experience ſhall finde it moſt fit for: And then his incloſed Ground, which now he is neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to keep for grazing (and is oftentimes over-grown with Moſs and other rubbiſh) he would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert to Tillage, which would for two or three Crops, with little coſt, bear twice ſo much Corn, as the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115804:8"/>
Common-field-ground uſually doth; if ſo (as I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it will be granted by experienced Husbandmen) then there will be a very great improvement by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſing of thoſe <hi>Common-fields;</hi> for if one Acre bear a double burthen, then there is not onely ſaved the one half of the ſeed, but alſo the one half of the work, which would be the Husbandmans great gain; for ſeed, and work to an Acre of Ground, is more then the Rent of four Acres of ſuch ordinary barren Field-ground (we now ſpeak of) comes to. Again, very much of ſuch light ground, in two or three years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter plowing, bears better graſs, then before it did, when not broken up; for ſuch ground calls for the plough once in twelve or fourteen years, and will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the Owner, not onely his ſeed (which the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-field Grounds</hi> come many years ſhort of) but alſo a good encreaſe, all clean, and without weeds.</p>
               <p>Another benefit to the Husbandman would be, that what remains after the Corn is taken off in Harveſt, would be ſo diſpoſed of in ſuch an orderly way, either by grazing of Cattel, or otherwiſe, which to him would be more beneficial, then in <hi>Common.</hi> I have often ſeen at the end of Harveſt, that men through covetouſneſs of having the firſt of the graſs in the <hi>Common-fields</hi> have thruſt in their Milch Cows, and have thought they have gained much thereby, in ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing two or three days graſs, when as indeed they have loſt five-fold more in their Cows milk, then they have ſaved by the graſs for their other Cattel. Experience hath told many, that the ſtubble, and graſs that is uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally growing amongſt the ſame, is of a dry benty na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which ſo dryeth up the milk, that it is ſeldom re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered at that time of the year, though again put in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115804:8"/>
better paſture: the like you ſhall finde if you put your Cows in any Meadow preſently after the mowing thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But ſome will object, <hi>That by incloſing, much ground is taken up with hedges and ditches; ſo what we get one way we loſe another.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of a square measuring sixty units on each side</figDesc>
                  <p>60</p>
                  <p>60</p>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115804:9"/>
               <head>SECT. IIII. <hi>Of Commons in rich Lowe grounds.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr the ſecond ſort of Commons, which are your rich Lowe grounds, though very fruitful, yet have I ſeen very little that might not be made more profitable to each mans particular (that hath a right thereunto) by encloſing: For though it may be truly ſaid of ſome part of this kinde of land, that it bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth as much now, as by Art it can be forced unto; yet I dare ſay, it is not ſo orderly diſpoſed of for the general good, as it might be, were it encloſed: for although it hath neither Buſh nor Bog, Moſs nor Furze, ſo that the Cattel have all the fruit; yet is not this in ſo orderly a way, (which Nature, as well as Policie, doth embrace) as otherwiſe it might be. For commonly all ſorts of cattel are put on ſuch grounds, though all good grounds are not good for all ſorts of cattel; for ſome good grounds are good to feed cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, that are not good for Milch Cows. I know ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch grounds, that if you put Milch Cows in them, they will feed ſo faſt, that preſently they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come dry, or yeeld very little milk. Other grounds are good for horſes and young beaſts, that are not good for ſheep. And if theſe rich grounds are kept till the graſs have a good head, yet there is uſually ſuch thruſting in at firſt, that the graſs is brought ſo ſhort, that horſes and ſheep muſt be put to a labour to live upon it: ſo that if it were encloſed, it might be ſo ordered, Some for Meadowing, and ſome for
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115804:10"/>
Paſture, and other ſuch uſes as the ſeveral owners ſhall finde it moſt fit, according to the ſeveral na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures thereof.</p>
               <p>I may compare the diſorderly feeding in thoſe Common grounds, to an unskilful Maſter of a Ship, that having his ſhip well victualled for a long voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, at his firſt going out is ſo prodigal thereof, that much more then what may well ſerve, is quickly waſted: but if he meet with a croſs winde, (as often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it falls out) then well if they can with ſmall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance keep themſelves from ſtarving; which an orderly diſpoſing with providence at the firſt, would have prevented.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V. <hi>Of Commons which are plain Upland grounds.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr the third ſort of Commons, which are plain Upland grounds, ſuch as the Downs in <hi>Hampſhire, Wiltſhire,</hi> and many other Weſtern Counties; which are more fit for Sheep then any other cattel: of which there will not be ſuch an extraordinary bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by encloſing, as by the other three ſorts of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon next to be treated of. And it is not my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to force arguments that have not apparent rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in them; for ſhould I do ſo, I ſhould tranſgreſs my own Law. The work in hand is of a high na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and I know, before it comes to application, it will be well weighed by wiſe men; and where the reaſons given prove but a grain too light, they ſhall be caſt by: and I am not over-confident of the ſucceſs.</p>
               <p>I know there are many that have ſet themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115804:10"/>
it. I have long deſired that ſome of more able parts then my ſelf would have taken the diſcourſe of this ſubject upon them; and earneſtly deſire, that the Reaſons I here give, with their own, may be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved to the advantage of the Publike, which in this is my aim.</p>
               <p>If this doth but prepare the mindes of ſome Country-men (who are Common proof, and are now led more by Tradition then Reaſon; who have no more to ſay for this, then for their Religion; It was thought well of by our fore-fathers, and they were as wiſe then, as you are now, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> to a willingneſs, when thoſe that are in Authority (and Truſtees for their good) ſhall do them good againſt their will (for againſt the wills of many it muſt be, or elſe it never will be) by Commiſſioning ſuch as they ſhall think fit in each County, for the work; if ſo, then my labour will not be loſt. I endeavour no more the encloſing of Commons, then where the encloſing may redound to the Common Good. And therefore I ſay no more but this, (to thoſe that have an intereſt in ſuch Commons which are of the nature of this third ſort) That encloſing by good Quick-fences, would keep the ground warm, and it would be a good ſhelter in a ſtorm: and what ground ſoever of it is ſubject to Moſs, the Plough once or twice in twenty yeers would better it: and thoſe that have had experience will tell you, that change of feeding cattel will make the ground more fruitful: As for example, that ground you uſually keep for your Paſture, if you graze it but one or two yeers with ſheep, it ſhall be far more fruitful for milk
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115804:11"/>
two or three yeers after. Again, oftentimes we ſee dainty Springs that run ſtealing thorow ſome plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant bottoms; which if encloſed, would be of very great uſe either for raiſing of Corn, Paſturage for Cattel, or pleaſant Groves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VI. <hi>Of Commons which are apt for Wood, and over-ſpread with Buſhes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr this fourth ſort of Common, to wit, Wood-ground, if encloſed, the improvement would be very great; for now there is little wood, little graſs, very few ſheep, no corn; ſo that five acres of this land now, doth not produce ſo much fruit as one acre would do if encloſed; for now the ground is ſo over-ſpread with buſhes, that there is little elſe but a ſhady fowre graſs, which is of no other uſe but for the breed of young beaſts and horſes; and thoſe there bred, are of ſmall growth.</p>
               <p>And as for the wood, it is ſeldom that any young plant ſteals thorow the midſt of a buſh, &amp; ſo eſcapes the cattels nipping; and if it doth eſcape the mouth of cattel, and come to ſome growth, yet it is then as ſeldom ſeen that it eſcapes the (indeed violent) hands of men: for uſually if it come thus far, it muſt ſuffer a remove, either to the fire, or to the hedge, or to ſome other ſuch like uſes. But if it haply eſcapes all theſe, yet it is ſtill liable to ſuch lopping and topping, that it cometh to be but a knotty pollard; and at laſt, after it hath long cumbred the ground, it ſerves for no more
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115804:11"/>
at beſt but for a doted log to lie behinde the fire.</p>
               <p>And as for the young cattel that are there bred, their feed is ſo much upon Hazel, Oak, or Hawthorn-buſhes, that their teeth are worn to ſtumps before they come to be four yeers old. And if ſome ſheep are in the winter put there for ſhelter, and that when deep ſnow is, they may feed on the buſhes; yet they leave there hanging much of their fine wool, for a requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal of their ſafety.</p>
               <p>Now were theſe Commons encloſed, it would much redound to the benefit of the Commonwealth, and to every of thoſe in particular that have a right therein: for many Commons of this nature are very good grounds, and there may be found good paſtures for the rearing or feeding of ſheep and all other ſorts of cattel; ſo that the ſame quantity of land which in ſuch Commons will now maintain but twenty cattel, (and thoſe of ſmall bone) would then maintain one hundred of very large growth. There may in many places thereof be had goodly Meadows, and other parts may be fit for Corn, and ſome other parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of not ſo fit for any of the laſt mentioned uſes, yet very apt for wood, and would produce very gallant trees, which in a few yeers will be precious in this Nation, if ſome ſpeedy courſe be not taken for the preſervation of timber.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VII. <hi>Commons cumbred with Thorns, Briers, Heath, Moſs,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p>THe fifth ſort of Commons, which are cumbred with thorns, briers, furzes, fern, heath, moſs,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115804:12"/>
and ſuch like unprofitable fruit, the ſoil thereof is in many places ſo peſtilent both to cattel and ſheep, by reaſon of thoſe many Gaules, Mooriſh Bogs, and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nkered Puddles or Lakes, that it it occaſions ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſeaſes, as the Mountain-evil, the Giddy, the Rot, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nay, there is ſuch an unkindlineſs in many of theſe grounds, that it hath an influence on the very bodies of men that inhabit thoſe parts; all which might be made both healthful and fruitful, were they encloſed; and great increaſe would accrue thereby, of all ſorts of cattel, ſheep, corn, and wood, to every man, both poor and rich, that hath his particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt therein; and ſo be both honourable and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial to the Commonwealth in general.</p>
               <p>I dare ſay, that many of you that have your enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures neer thoſe vaſt Commons which are mountain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and bleak, can ſay that your now-encloſed grounds would be much more fruitful, were thoſe Commons encloſed alſo: for it is often ſeen, that thoſe cutting windes that have their free paſſage the row many vaſt Commons, and alſo the thick miſts that are occaſioned by thoſe rotten boggie grounds, cauſeth much unkindlineſs both in corn and graſs: for, in the time of your corn-blowing, you ſay thoſe bleak windes blow the bloſſoms off (the ear) before it be ripe, ſo that the grain in the ear is ſmall and horny, and will yeeld but very little flour, eſpecially in the top and bottom thereof. And in harveſt theſe windes have oftentimes ſuch a clear paſſage, without any interpoſition (of hedges or trees) that the ripeſt and beſt corn is blown forth before it comes to the Sickle.</p>
               <p>Again, look on your Commons with an indifferent
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115804:12"/>
judgement, and tell me if you have not ſeen much of it of which you can ſay, that that piece which now bears little elſe but Moſs, and rubbiſh matter, were it encloſed would bear excellent Corn. And do you not look on another piece of Mooriſh ground that now bears little but Peny-graſs, or by ſome called Liver-graſs (which kills many thouſands of your ſheep yeer by yeer) and you finde the very form and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of it in their Livers, and can ſay that the ſheeps feeding on ſuch ground kills them; and can alſo ſay, that much of that ground, were it encloſed and drained, would be worth ten or twenty ſhillings the acre by the yeer, which now is worth leſs then no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, for that it breeds the Rot and many other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes in your ſheep, to their great mortality, and no little loſs to the Commonwealth? And I pray tell me (if you can) of any man that ever went about to better ſuch ground thus in Common, by expending five ſhillings thereon, though ſo much would better the ground five pounds twice told: for my part, I can hear of none; and knew I any ſuch, I would here name and commend him for a good Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths man. In this, the Proverb is good, That <hi>that which is every man's, is no man's:</hi> for no man takes care for the bettering of Commons.</p>
               <p>I dare ſay, had they ſuch grounds in the Low-Countries as many of our unprofitable Commons are, they would build Villages, Towns, and Cities, and maintain an hundred thouſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd families, which with us do not maintain many thouſands of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as now they are uſed.</p>
               <p>What, hath not God made us a Commonwealth as well as them? Are not we to bleſs God for it, by
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115804:13"/>
improving thoſe bleſſings he beſtows on us to the beſt advantage, that the many thouſands unborn may bleſs God for the Change he hath wrought for us, by putting the opportunity of doing good in our hands? If now then we neglect theſe excellent im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements, we may thank our ſelves; (the lot is caſt into the lap.) It puts not me alone, but all the world in admiration, what the Lord will do by us, that hath put three ſuch great Kingdoms into this our one Commonwealth, which naturally offer unto us ſuch variety of Improvements, that no one Nation of the world can parallel. Hath God given us ſo much rich ground that now lies Common (I may almoſt ſay uſeleſs) ſituate extraordinarily convenient to many Navigable Rivers, and offer themſelves very natural and apt for the planting of Woods, whereby our Shipping may be for ever maintained, and our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereby (ſo far as means can go) made ſtrong and ſafe? And hath God furniſhed us with all needful riches of Inland-commodities, that no one part of the world hath more, that are of ſo real a worth, and hath ſeated theſe Iſles of our Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth in the midſt of thoſe Seas that do abound with ſuch riches, that our neighbour-nation muſt be beholden to us for a great part of their livelihood; I mean, the variety of Fiſh and Fiſhing, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others cannot have without our leave (notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>mare liberum</hi> that floats in ſo many mens brains, who indeed have no Engliſh ſaltitude, and therefore too bad to have reſt on a dunghill? Set up then your Fiſhing Buſſes; and let thoſe twice fourty thouſand hands in building of Buſſes, and making of Nets, be an employment for our own Poor (that now
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115804:13"/>
are both idle and chargeable) which our neighbour-nation hath now the benefit of: and let not the greater good, by encloſing the Commons, be neglected: for thereby will be a great increaſe, and a good change, when ſixty acres of your Common ground that would not keep above ſixty ſheep, will then keep an hundred ſheep, ſix beaſts, and a horſe.</p>
               <p>I pray conſider, if one and twenty acres were plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſowed for two or three yeers, and then let lie for graſs again, if it would not keep more cattel and ſheep then ſixty ſix acres would do when it lay over-run with Moſs and other rubbiſh.</p>
               <p>It is verily believed by good experienced men, that the very ſraw and after-graſs that would ariſe from fourteen acres of the one and twenty acres kept in Tillage, will keep more cattel then all the ſixty ſix acres would do in ſuch Commons as now we treat of, if wiſely ordered according to the nature of the ſoyl, by turning Tillage into Paſture, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture into Tillage; which you may do (if encloſed) at your pleaſure, to your great advantage: and the dung that will be made of the ſtraw, will be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſupply to keep your ground in continual heart.</p>
               <p>I know very many Commons ſo large, that a Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder that hath not thirty three acres of Encloſure belonging to his tenement, would then by his right of Common have ſixtyſix acres more come to his ſhare, were the Commons encloſed. And were then thoſe ſixty ſix orderly diſpoſed of, (as thus) fourty two acres in Meadow and Paſture, and three acres to plant with Wood, and the other one and twenty acres in Tillage, to ſowe yeerly with Rye, Wheat, Barley, Oats, or what other kinde of grain it is moſt fit for.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115804:14"/>
If this orderly way were taken, the now-Freeholder, with this additional encloſure, might have a full em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment for his many children, which now in moſt parts are brought up very idly, having little to do but to look after a few ſheep ſcattering on the Common.</p>
               <p>The greateſt Objection againſt the encloſing of ſuch Commons as are over-ſpread with Heath, is, (ſay ſome)
<q>
                     <hi>Our cattel and ſheep will make a good ſhift to live on it in a hard Winter, when fodder is ſcarce.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It muſt be granted, that Neceſſity will force to Endeavour, eſpecially where it is for life: but as for nouriſhment by ſuch feeding, there is very little in your great old Heath, which oftentimes you are neceſſitated to put fire into, that ſo young Heath (that is tender) may come up for your Cattel, or otherwiſe that they may come to a better feed, which is the graſs that groweth at the bottom of ſuch Heath. And ſurely you would ſay, that could you turn it all to graſs, it would be much better, and a more thriving feed for your cattel. Nay, there are many, that could they have it encloſed at the worſt, (that is) if no better ſhould grow on it then Heath; yet ſo, they could make more benefit of it then as now, it lying in Common: for then, the poor man not able to ſtock, may rent out his ground; the richer man may ſo order it, that he may feed therein what cattel it is moſt agreeable unto: and then at all times he knows where to look for his cattel; but in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon he muſt oftentimes look for them two or three miles, and ſometimes more, there being neither gate nor hedge to keep them from ſtraying: and this gives great encouragement to a thieviſh heart to fall
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115804:14"/>
to ſtealing (which experience tells us in many large Commons:) ſo that if in the worſt condition, theſe and all other grounds would be more profitable if encloſed. But I know not any but that may be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved: there is much of this ground very good for Corn, eſpecially where the ſoyl is deep, and of a faſt earth. I have ſeen of this ſort of ground, that by the husbandry of Betting and Burning, there hath been a very great increaſe: and although this kinde of Husbandry is deſtructive to many fine grounds, where the ſoyl is ſhallow, as experience tells Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lords in <hi>Hampſhire,</hi> and in other places where the ſoyl is of the like nature, (where none but ſhort leaſed te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants have the benefit of this husbandry;) yet where the ground is cold, and the ſoyl deep, there this huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry may be called good.</p>
               <p>And if the ſoyl be hollow, looſe, and black, like your Mooriſh ground, it will bear excellent good Oats (a Grain no whit inferiour to that we have in moſt eſteem amongſt us:) and the plowing of ſuch ground doth beget a very good graſs. If you look on the Foreſt of <hi>Windſor,</hi> in which there are many places of it as bad grounds of this Heathy nature (as ever I ſaw) yet the Encloſures adjoynining (though but a Hedge between) doth produce either Corn, Graſs, or Wood; and ſurely the worſt of that bad, where it encloſed (with husbandry) would be much bettered; therefore ſeeing the worſt may be much improved, be you encouraged that God hath given but one ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent of ability unto in this way of improvement; wrap it not up in a Napkin, but exerciſe your parts, and be at ſome little coſt in ſetting poor labourers on work, to encloſe by ditching and ſetting Quick; let there
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115804:15"/>
be but care taken to make choice of ſuch kinds of ſets your ground is moſt apt for, as alſo to plant it at fit ſeaſons of the year, and truſt God with the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. For there's no ground in <hi>England,</hi> but, with good Husbandry, will bear ſome kind of wood or other (except it be ſome land neer the Sea-ſide:) The bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit that will come to many hereby, will be ſeen quickly to haſten the encreaſe of all Husbandry, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactory, Trade, &amp; the greateſt Merchandiſe: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my deſire to all my Country-men is, that you would not content your ſelves to hear or ſee theſe improvements afar off, but labour to bring it home with your owne hands, and your enjoyments ſhall be very great: Petition thoſe that are in Authority that they would Commiſſion ſuch that may with wiſdome and all indifference draw out the lines, ſo to make the Divident, that there may be no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining; but all might rejoyce to ſee the poor made rich, and the rich yet more rich.</p>
               <p>How pleaſurable and how profitable would it be to ſee one part of the Commons converted to Corn, another part to Meadowing, another to Paſture, and another part to dainty Groves, and pleaſant Woods; and to ſee the man that lived very poor, and his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny children wandering from door to door begging their bread, now all of them employed, ſome plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſome planting, ſome milking Cows of their own, and joyfully eating the fruit of their own labour!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:115804:15"/>
               <head>SECT. VIII. <hi>Which treateth of Forests and Chaſes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Sixth ſort of Commons are thoſe of Foreſts and Chaſes. Of theſe I need ſay but little; all mens eyes are on them, and every mans judgement can reach to ſay, that Encloſures here would be of ſingular advantage to the Commonwealth. If you would have asked the Country-man that lived neer thoſe Foreſts, and had right of Common therein (when his honeſt and painful labour had raiſed his hopes to a crop of good Corn) but thirty yeers ago, whether he would have been willing to have the Foreſt encloſed, He would have ſaid, Yea, with all his heart. If you had asked him whether it would have been good for the Commonwealth in general, he would then have ſaid, Yes ſure; and would have given you many reaſons for it: one rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon would have been, We now lie under Foreſt-laws, which are made chiefly for the preſerving of Deer; which is very prejudicial not only to us here living, in particular, but to the Commonwealth in general. As for our own Encloſures, we cannot make the beſt advantage of them; we dare not: for if we do, what with Hunting, and the Deers feeding, we have moſt of our Corn ſpoiled: and if five hundred Deer lie in our Corn all night, and we kill any one of them, it is a hanging matter. And if we keep but a dog (eſpecially with claws) to hunt them out, upon
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115804:16"/>
any diſpleaſure taken by an under Ranger, we ſhould preſently be complained of, and our puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would be greater then the loſs of all our corn. Another reaſon would be, that in many Foreſts ſheep are no Commonable cattel; and ſurely this is a great prejudice to the Commonwealth; for Wool is one of the greateſt riches in <hi>England:</hi> and had we that benefit of keeping ſheep, then our ſervants which we are neceſſitated to keep (all the yeer for Summers work) and our children, would have a full employment in the Winter, by Carding, and Spinning, and Knitting: then we ſhould not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make Cloth for our own families (which now we buy) but for others alſo; and it would be a good means to advance our Clothing for forraign Trade, and many hands would thereby be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed.</p>
               <p>And were the Foreſts and Chaſes encloſed, by the wiſe ordering of them, there would be a great advantage to the Commonwealth: for then there may be care taken that the Foreſt of <hi>Dean,</hi> ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for Ship-timber (not to be parallel'd) might again flouriſh with goodly trees; which to waſte, comes not far ſhort of Treaſon: and that goodly Foreſt of <hi>Waltham,</hi> ſo apt for Wood and Graſs, and lying ſo convenient to a Navigable River, may abound with Cattel, and gallant Timber: And that Upland and now-Buſhie Chaſe of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> will then be loaded with Corn and Sheep.</p>
               <p>And do not thoſe rich grounds in <hi>Needwood-Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt</hi> (or Chaſe) and that large Foreſt of <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> with many more of the like or better nature,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115804:16"/>
all offer themſelves, with abundance of fruitfulneſs to this Nation, were they encloſed?</p>
               <p>Surely the great increaſe of Riches to this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, cannot but be foreſeen by wiſe men, if thoſe fruitful grounds now lying in Common, and much of it waſte and unoccupied, were once encloſed: inſomuch that thoſe good Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths-men that have their eyes upon it, will ſay, and do believe, that were the Commons enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, there would be ſufficient for a third part of people more then are now in <hi>England.</hi> (I do not go ſo high.) Others think, were they encloſed, they would maintain an eighth part more. (My thoughts are not ſo lowe.)</p>
               <p>But many there are which do believe (of which I am one) that, were they encloſed, there would be plenty for a fifth part more, and employment for many hundred thouſand labouring hands more then are now in <hi>England,</hi> which this Nation (ſo apt for Procreation) is now neceſſitated to part with (for want of employment;) and to other Plantations they go, where the Air is no whit agreeable to their conſtitutions, and ſo they quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly return to their duſt; which for many yeers (till theſe Commons were fully peopled) by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſing would be in a very great meaſure pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, and we ſhould here at home enjoy the benefit of their endeavours with us; which would greatly enrich and ſtrengthen us: for thereby (if need ſhould be) there would in few yeers be added to our gallant Souldiery an Auxiliary of twenty thouſand men, able and ready to oppoſe any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Enemy, either by Sea or Land.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115804:17"/>
I might have added many more Reaſons, for an encouragement to the encloſing of Commons, and anſwered ſome toyiſh Objections, with which I am not willing to ſwell up this Book, for that it would make it more tedious to the judicious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <p>If that which hath been ſaid do but point out the great good to the Commonwealth which at firſt I laid down in my three general grounds, I ſhall therein rejoyce, when others, and thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred thouſands, ſhall receive the benefit thereof.</p>
               <p>I cannot ſee wherein it ſhould be doubted of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then of a very great increaſe of all neceſſary Commodities which our Nation doth naturally af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, if thoſe many fruitful Commons were enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: for then we ſhould have ſuch variety of ſoyls, that we might very plentifully be furniſhed with thoſe Commodities which come from other Countries, and we now are many times neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitated to be beholden to them for, as Corn, which ſome yeers were we not ſupplied with from other parts, we ſhould be brought to great ſtraits: which by Gods bleſſing on the Husbandmans la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in thoſe rich grounds in many Commons, would be prevented. And much of that ground which now lieth waſte, would be very apt for Hemp and Flax (commodities too much neglected amongſt us) and we thereby might employ ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hands of our own, and be very plentifully fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with the moſt needful Linen, which now in a great part we have from other Countries.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:115804:17"/>
As for the benefit which will be to this Nation, by drayning and ſevering the Fenns, every one may now ſee, as in the rich feedings, the getting of Corn, Hemp, and Flax, the abundance of Oyle, and many others, all which at the firſt undertaking was very much op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by many thouſands, who do enjoy, and can ſpeak of (by good experience) the great commodities that thoſe Countries receive thereby.</p>
               <p>Another increaſe of the Native Commodities by incloſing, will be in Cattell and Wood; for much of thoſe grounds that yeeld but little now (other then Moſſe, Furze, Brackin, and ſuch unfruitfull matter) would then produce fruitfull graſſe, which would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound much to the increaſe of all ſort of cattell, and the increaſe of timber will not be the leaſt commodity; the late decay thereof our enemies did rejoyce in, as ſome can well remember, when thoſe notable Popiſh Politicians (Sir <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn Winter,</hi> Sir <hi>Bazill Brooks,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Minn, Rome's</hi> Agents) had deſigned the deſtruction of thoſe goodly woods in the Forreſt of <hi>Dean,</hi> and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our friends cannot take any great joy in the great waſt that hath been made ſince.</p>
               <p>And what a great ſtrength to our Nation ſhipping is, and what a multitude of people are employed, and maintained thereby, is very viſible to all wiſe men: I dare not enter into particulars, for ſhould I, they are ſo many, they would make a great volume, and my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of half an hours reading would be diſappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p>It is ſeen by many, that Trade and Manufactory doth very much depend upon our preſerving and improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Native commodities; all forreign commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties muſt be obtained by thoſe of our own Country.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115804:18"/>
Now thoſe which chiefly maintain forreign commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, are fiſh (I call it ours, for we have had preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for many Ages, that which the Law of Nations (if it be granted that there be any) doth maintaine as one of its pureſt begotten Iſſue) Wooll, Tin, and Lead; and although many of our other Native commodities are of more abſolute neceſſity, yet theſe are not to be neglected; and it's not to be doubted, but our God, who hath ſo wonderfully bleſt our faithfull Truſtees with wiſdome to this day, will be ſtill with them in their Chriſtian care, and willing endeavours in theſe ſo neceſſary works for the univerſall good of all (the three Nations now united) in this our Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and here though collaterally to my work, I muſt ſay that that Noble Act of making conquered <hi>Scotlond</hi> one free body with us, (and what if our Sea neighbours were thus incorporated) a Maxime which the Romane and Venetian States never admitted, may be more ſubſervient to common liberty, then thirty Armies, but enough of this diſh at this ſeaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IX. <hi>The way and manner of incloſing Commons.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MAny will ſay the work of it ſelf is good, if ſuch a way might be found that might preſerve each mans right.</p>
               <p>Now if I might have but this granted me, that it is but right that the poore ought to be maintained one way or other, (which ſurely good men will confeſſe) then do but obſerve theſe my humble Propoſalls,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115804:18"/>
and I doubt not but ſatisfaction will be given.</p>
               <p>Firſt, then for all thoſe Commons in which men have an undivided right, for to them only I ſhall now direct the remaining part of my diſcourſe. Let the Commons in <hi>England,</hi> in this I except <hi>Wales,</hi> having for them a further intention, be divided into foure e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall parts, and let one of theſe four be firſt ſet a part for the good of the poor, to the uſes following.</p>
               <p>Out of this fourth part, let the preſent Cottagers be firſt provided for, and let reſpect be had to the number of each Family, that ſo allowance may be made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, and let twenty, thirty, or forty Acres, more or leſſe be laid to every Cottage: as for example, if there be a Common of twelve hundred Acres, out of that let three hundred Acres be allotted for the poor. Now ſuppoſe you have of poor four Families that are Cottagers, the one having four, the other ſix, the third eight, and the fourth ten perſons in their ſeverall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, if it ſhall be thought fit, let there be twenty A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres allowed to the firſt, thirty Acres to the ſecond, forty Acres to the third, and fifty Acres to the fourth, in all one hundred and forty Acres: ſo of the firſt fourth part, there will be one hundred and ſixty Acres re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining; out of which one hundred and ſixty acres, it would do well to conſider the number of poor that are in each Pariſh, beſides thoſe that have Cottages on the Commons, and are maintained by the Pariſh, and that one third or fourth part, more or leſſe, be allowed to that Pariſh for a conſtant relief of their poor.</p>
               <p>This being done, let thoſe Cottagers, to whom this land ſhall ye allotted, have a leaſe thereof for terme of years, or for two or three lives, and that at a very eaſie rent, not to be more then the fifth part of the preſent
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115804:19"/>
truevalue, reſpect being had to the charges of inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and fencing thereof; as thus, if the Land be worth twenty pence the acre <hi>per annum,</hi> and there be thirty acres laid to a Cottage, then let the Cottager pay du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his life ſeven, eight, or ten ſhillings yearly at the moſt, and by this means, he that is poor this year, will be made rich in a very few years after, for there will be now employment for the many hands in his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſome digging and planting both in garden and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard, ſome ploughing for Corne, Hemp, and Flax, ſome one way, ſome another, all carefully labouring with their hands, that ſo they may enjoy the fruit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               <p>Ob. <hi>But it will be asked how the rent reſerved on theſe Cottages, as alſo the improvement at the expiration of their leaſes, and likewiſe the remainder of the fourth part of the Common ſhall be employed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> I anſwer, let the remainder of the fourth part, not diſpoſed of to the Cottagers, be let by leaſe, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe for a yearly rent, and let that rent, and the reſerved rent on the Cottagers, with their improved rent upon the expiration of the leaſes, be imployed in raiſing work-houſes, and ſtock to ſet the poor on work in thoſe places moſt needfull, which I look on as a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving way, for the ſupply of the decaies in ſtock, for lack of which heretofore many worthy undertakings have in a ſhort time fallen to the ground; for it is not to be expected, that the increaſe of ſuch works ſhould maintain themſelves, by reaſon that ſuch works have many Overſeers, and Directors that muſt be maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a Salary; and ſomething muſt be allowed to ſupply the defects of thoſe weaker hands, that cannot get ſufficient for their own livelyhood; and the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115804:19"/>
would be great to the Common-wealth, if the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, in ſome ſerviceable commodittes, would main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain but the one half of thoſe idle perſons that go wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring, and now live by filching, ſtealing, roguing, drabbing, and beg from door to door.</p>
               <p>I have many times offered to many of thoſe idle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, both men and women, ſix pence by the day to work, they have anſwered, <hi>they cannot live on it, and as good play for nothing, as work for nothing.</hi> By which it may be gathered, that they like drones, never labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, do ſpend out of that which others labour for, each of them ſix pence a day, ſo that if there be but two hundred thouſand of theſe idle perſons in <hi>England,</hi> and but the one halfe of them able to work; there is a daily waſt to the Common-wealth of two thouſand five hundred pounds, which amounts unto <hi>per annum</hi> nine hundred twelve thouſand five hundred pounds, a ſum that would help well toward the maintaining of a gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Army. Now if but one halfe of this were got by their work, and the other half ſupplied, it would be a great ſaving to this Nation yearly. If then you would reform theſe great evills, incloſe your Commons, and down with thoſe many thouſands of blind Alehouſes, which are fit for nothing but to uphold drunkenneſſe, idleneſſe, roguery, whoredome, and increaſe beggery and erect workhouſes, for this is one great meanes to make the poor rich, and the rich yet more rich; and were theſe many idle perſons ſet to work, it would not only be an inrichment of, but a great honor to our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> But here it will be objected, <hi>that many of theſe Cottages are new erections, and ought not by the Statute to be ſuffered or continned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:115804:20"/>
                  <hi>An.</hi> My anſwer is, that you have either given way to the building of them for the eaſe of your Pariſh, or out of a baſe fear of your Lord. The Pariſh ſometimes wants habitation for their poor, and then with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Lord there is a new erection, and for which there are very few Lords, but contrary to Law do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive rent, ſo that he careth not how many are erected. Again, many times the Lord gives way to erect with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſent, either of Free, or Copyholder, and if ſuch are preſented, yet very ſeldome redreſſed<hi>:</hi> The Statute doth as well ſay, that the poor being admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and continued a ſhort time in the Pariſh, they have a right of habitation within the Pariſh, and muſt be provided for: but ſuch hath beene the cruelty of the former incloſers, that not only thoſe new Erections, but old and new all together have been thruſt our, and Might hath herein (as too often) overcome right, and thereby the poor inhabitants neceſſitated to ſeek their bread from door to door, which doubtleſſe hath been a crying ſin, and it is very like that thoſe which have ſo done, have had the curſe of theſe poore fallen on them, or their Families: therefore my advice is, that they all be provided for proportionably accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the number of their Families, and then you may expect a bleſſing; for the Lord hath ſaid it, <hi>Bleſſed are the mercifull.</hi> And here caſt thy bread on the waters, and thou ſhalt find it after many daies; ages to come ſhall bleſſe God that ſuch mercy hath been ſhewen in our daies, and that common curſe ſhall be turned into a bleſſing to your childrens children for many Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>For the other three parts, let the one fourth go to the Lord, and the other three to the Free and Copyhold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115804:20"/>
that have a right thereunto, or rather let the Free and Copy holders have the whole, and pay the Lord an eaſie quit rent for each acre that ſhall be encloſed.</p>
               <p>But whoſoever incloſeth, let him be ſtrictly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, that every twentieth acre, beſides hedges, be planted with wood, which may be ſo ordered, that to ſuch grounds it will be a great good, and time may make it of much advantage to the Common-wealth, eſpecially where near navigable rivers, for preſerving of wood will not be the leaſt advantage to this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Countrey men put it in practiſe? what with your hedges, and thoſe dainty ſcattered little groves in which you will not only have a great delight, but much profit; for it will keep your ground warme, and thereby make it more fruitfull, it will be a good ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, both to your corn, ſheep, and other cattell; you may bedeck your hedges with Pear-trees, and Apple-trees, in which you will find a great increaſe, and take much pleaſure. Let the example of <hi>Worceſter</hi> and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reford</hi> ſhires invite you to this. Again, let the incloſers be enjoyned to leave good large high<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>waies, and ſo left to be by them maintained; but as for thoſe large Commons in <hi>Wales;</hi> and here may be taken in <hi>Yorkſhire, Lancaſhire,</hi> and other of thoſe Northern Counties, that do abound with Commons and ignorance, I deſire it may be conſidered, if not requiſite to a quiet in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, that learning be furthered, and that by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding thoſe large Commons into five equall parts, and that one fifth part thereof ſhould be ſubdivided, the one Moyety thereof to maintain a free Schoole in every Pariſh, to teach the Engliſh letter, which ſome poor honeſt man or woman would undertake for a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſmal ſtipend, between five or ten pounds <hi>per annum,</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:115804:21"/>
and all mens children ſhould there be taught freely; and if the Pariſhes lie neer and convenient, then one School may ſerve two Pariſhes, this would incourage the poor to ſend their children ſometimes, when they have little to do for them, and thereby attain to ſome little learning, which would tend much to the civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of them, and all may acquire ſo much, as may make them fit for a higher School.</p>
               <p>The other Moyety of the fifth part may be well im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed for the maintenance of a Latine free Schoole, and theſe to be ſo ſeated in the ſeverall Counties, that men need not ſend their children above five or ſix miles at fartheſt, if ſo, then poor men would be incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to ſend their children on Munday morning, with a loaf and a cheeſe, or what other proviſion they could afford, and have them return home on Saturday night, whereby they may look to them themſelves, &amp; not be at charges for others to do it, this little part of thoſe vaſt Commons thus imployed, would not be loſt, but found to be of great advantage to their Poſterity.</p>
               <p>I am ſure the preſent conſtitution of Schools is ſuch, as argues a deficiency in our young Government; and I judge the education of youth is more influentiall than judged by many pretenders to skill in civill Government; and there are notions of this ſubject, which if applied, after a few years, each of them may be of a more conſervative nature to our home-peace then thouſand armed men: and as to proficiency in learning, it is not the <hi>Genius</hi> of youth in generall, but as now the eſtates of a few rich parents, that force the uninclined child to ſeek knowledge, not knowing that who ever is wiſe is born ſo, and that learning is but the improvement of natural reaſon, which is graduated according to the conſtitution.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:115804:21"/>
The other four parts may be diſpoſed of, as before is adviſed.</p>
               <p>But the carrying on of this work from firſt to laſt, muſt be by that great authority of Parliament; it is to be wiſhed it might be done by theſe in preſent power, that ſo this may be in the Catalogue of their other ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good works, for it will not be the leaſt; and that by commiſſioning ſome in each County, men both diſcreet and honeſt, a greater want then that of money, ſo that with all indifferency they make the divident without partiality to each (according to their ſeverall intereſts) their due proportion; if this courſe be taken, the ſucceſſe will be good, for God will give a bleſſing thereunto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>SECT. X. <hi>Treating of the manner of incloſing Forreſts and Chaces, with ſome brief directions for planting and preſerving Wood, that ſo it may be a proviſion for our Navy to all Generations.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw for the encloſing of Forreſts and Chaces, a work of very great concernment, and ought to be warily handled by the moſt able and wiſeſt men) thoſe that have a right of Common in theſe, yet have not ſuch priviledges as thoſe others, that have a right to moſt of thoſe Commons formerly ſpoken of; and therefore are not to expect ſo large a proportion to their own particular. For many of ſuch, who live within the Regard of the Forreſts, heretofore would have been glad to have parted with their right of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:115804:22"/>
upon condition they might have freely enjoyed the like priviledges as other men in their own particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar land encloſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For beſides their ſpoil in corn, their paſtures and mowing graſſe may in ſome ſort be ſaid to be common, for they muſt leave places on purpoſe in their hedges for the Deer to come in, and when they were in and lodged, they might not diſturb them, and fortheir Woods they may not fall any without li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, and many ſuch like inconveniences. But what is each mans particular right to the ſoil, and what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion ought to be allowed them, I ſhal not preſcribe, but leave it to their wiſdome, who have a power to diſpoſe of more or leſſe, to each man as they ſhall ſee good reaſon for.</p>
               <p>I ſhall only ſpeak to the manner of incloſing and diſpoſing, and in that I ſhal deſire conſideration might be had to the preſerving of Timber for a conſtant and certain ſupply of the Navy.</p>
               <p>As firſt to ſet apart ſo much ground as is moſt apt for Wood, and moſt neer adjoyning to a navigable ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, not diſtant above three or four miles; and of this ground ſo fit and convenient, there may be found thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thouſand acres for that purpoſe; as a great part of the Forreſt of <hi>Dean</hi> neer <hi>Severn</hi> ſide, ſome part of the new Forreſt neer the Sea. That which is moſt apt for Wood in the Forreſt of <hi>Windſor</hi> neer the Thames, much of <hi>Waltham</hi> Forreſt, and <hi>Enfield</hi> Chace, many other places there be as convenient as theſe, out of which may be preſerved from ſale, ſo much as would for after ages be ſufficient to build and maintain ſhipping, if carefully kept, to all Generations; for this purpoſe, let there be choice made of men skilfull<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> induſtrious, and faithful, to whoſe care the charge of planting and preſerving
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115804:22"/>
ſhall be committed. Thoſe who are employed for that purpoſe, muſt firſt ſee that the grounds be wel fenced with pale or quick, or rather both, with a good M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>und and Dich, that all ſort; of cattell may be kept out; for if any cattell come in, before the trees are growne ſo high as to be out of their reach, there will be very much ſpoil made, then let there be ſo many acres prepared by ploughing or digging, as may be well compaſſed to plant that year, and ſo yearly till all the ground be planted, either by ſetting young ſets, or ſowing of acornes, but ſowing of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cornes is to be preferred before the other, for they will ſooner come to perfection, and be both ſtreight and tall: beſides theſe ſpringing up thick may be removed the next year, but then with them muſt be tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n up a good quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of earth, and little holes prepared for them, or rather ploughed furrowes in the place, to which you remove them: when you thus firſt fit your ground with the plough, raiſe it up in little ridges, and then you may with a light plough make a furrow on each ſide the Ridge, and if your Ridge be big enough, let there be one furrow on the top thereof; in theſe furrowes you may put your a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corns indifferently thick, but let your furrowes be two foot aſunder, that ſo you may with more ſafety goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween, to weed or remove as you ſtill ſhall have occaſion. Theſe plants ſhould be dreſſed by hoeing or kybing for two or three years, that ſo the weeds may be killed, and freſh earth put to the plants, till of themſelves they top the weeds or graſſe; but if you uſe the Hoe, take heed you bruiſe not the plants, for if you do, they carry it with them till they come to be trees; theſe may grow together to thirty years growth, and ſo they will preſerve each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the winds: if the wind have a ful ſtroak at them, and they thin, it will bend them, and ſometimes bruiſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115804:23"/>
them, which many times is the cauſe of that in Timber which we call <hi>Cup,</hi> or <hi>VVindſhakes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At thirty years let them be garbled, taking the worſt away by grubbing or cutting, leaving the moſt kindly plants for Timber, which wood ſo taken away, may be ſold, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe diſpoſed of, as the State ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l think fit, this would be again done, when they come to be of ſeventy or eighty years growth, leaving ſtill the moſt kindly for Timber; each tree then ſhould have ten foot of ground to ſpread it ſelf in, and ſo you may expect in each acre, on this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, four hundred and eighty trees (if none miſcarry) ſo that after two hundred years, if you reſerve thirty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand acres, you may have one hundred and fifty acres yearly at a good full growth for your uſe, which may be diſpoſed of as the State ſhall ſtil ſee cauſe; and when great trees are made uſe of, it were good they were ſtocked up by the roots, for if cut, then the roots wil cumber the ground ſo, that there cannot be a new planting till theſe roots are rotten, which will be long, or elſe there muſt be a ſtocking after the fall, which will be far more chargeable then if they had been ſtocked at the firſt; beſides if you cut a tree down, there's great waſt of Timber; for the kirfe (if it be a great tree) is ſo deep, that uſually there's five or ſix foot of ſquare Timber loſt, being hewed into chips, which would be ſaved if ſtocked up, and ſawed cloſe to the root; if you cleave this great root, and make it into Charcoale, it will pay the charge: the hole in the ground out of which the great root is taken muſt be levelled with the plough, or otherwiſe filled up, for if you ſet any plant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in that place, it ſeldome ever cometh to be a kindly tree, the old tree by her many great roots having ſucked from the earth that which was moſt fit for nouriſhment; therefore it ſhould be often ploughed before it will be fit
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115804:23"/>
to plant again, and if it were ſowed with corn a yeare or two after, before it be again planted, it would be much better: Theſe brief directions I thought fit to inſert for the help of thoſe not experienced skilfull, if it ſhould happen ſuch ſhould be called to this work.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> But it will be objected, <hi>that this way will be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry chargeable to the Common-wealth, and long before a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny profit will come to the ſame thereby.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> I anſwer, it is naturall for man to labour for po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, his children being truly ſaid to be his more li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving parts, and it is God that giveth man that provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; had not God inclined mans heart to this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, we had had but little Timber to build Ships with at this time. It is ſaid of the Indians in <hi>China,</hi> that the great Grandfather prepares the earth (that our fine <hi>China</hi> diſhes are made of) for the great Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child to reap the benefit of it two hundred years after, and ſurely if they do this for the inriching of a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, we ought to do much more for a generall ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and it's better begun once then never; ſome will ſay, that's never long, which comes at laſt.</p>
               <p>Another objection is, <hi>that we have many Plantations, as New-England, and others, out of which we have very good and plenty of Timber, and we can have this brought at a cheaper rate, then we can bring our own now grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to our Docks, or Wharfes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, for bringing Timber to the Wharfes or Docks, when you fetch it ten or fifteen miles from a navigable river, it cannot be expected to come at a cheape rate; but if this courſe be taken, to plant neer navigable rivers, it cannot be reaſonably imagined, that it ſhould be cheaper farther fetched, then neer at hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:115804:24"/>
And to truſt to foreign plantations for our Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, I hope it will be the wiſdome of the State to do otherwiſe then rely on uncertainties deficiency; If we ſhould have difference with other Nations, their work would be to cut off our ſupplies, which our own practiſe teacheth; if we beſiege a Town or Caſtle, we preſently inquire after their chief ſupply, and can we but cut off their conduit pipes, we know the place wil be quickly ours; it's good and ſure work to have our ſupplies within our ſelves, and if the enemies ſhould once find that we were defective in Timber for ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, it would be a greater incouragement to them, than if we were in want of money to pay our ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; for the affection of man can ſupply this want, but nothing can the other. And it's the wiſdome of a State in all things of great concernment, to take the ſafeſt way, and not put themſelves upon uncertainties, if poſſible it may be otherwiſe; if it be but in ſo ſmall a matter as bringing the Records from the <hi>Tower</hi> to <hi>Westminſter,</hi> although they may probably come ſafely by water for twelve pence, yet it is accounted pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to have them carried by Land, though it uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally coſts three or four ſhillings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> It is farther objected, <hi>that if our Plantations fail, yet our trade will fetch both Timber and Ships at all times, as the</hi> Hollanders <hi>now do that have no Timber growing, for it's uſually ſaid, that though trade be ſick, it will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver die.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> To theſe I anſwer, it is not good to adventure a ſickneſſe, when we may be ſure of a continuated health; the beſt uſe of ſickneſſe is, that we may ſee there's a great happineſſe in health, and thoſe that have been in ſome deſperate diſeaſe, will take care to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115804:24"/>
the falling into it again, and the diſeaſe of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in trade may be ſuch, as that it may ſeize not only on the humours, but on the very ſpirits of a Common-wealth; in which, though thoſe guided by ſenſe cannot diſcerne, yet thoſe of reaſon find it to be of a more deadly nature then the former; thereby we may be made as unable to help our ſelves as the <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chemites</hi> were. The ſtory is famous of that almoſt u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſall league at <hi>Cambray,</hi> by Pope <hi>Julius</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and moſt of the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> againſt poor <hi>Venice,</hi> whom becauſe emulated (which may be our caſe) by all the Neighbour Nations, they would have deſtroyed her as at once, and ſo had done, had ſhe not moſt ſubtilly complemented with the Emperor, bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Pope, ſtrained her ſelf to nothing, that ſhe might have but a being in the world. If ſuch a league as this be within two yeares of this time, it will teach us ſuch a one may be in future ages.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Hollanders</hi> indeed have been a provident people, and have their ſtores before hand, and have kept peace with thoſe from whom they have had their greateſt ſupply of Timber; but there's no ſuch thing intailed on them, that they ſhall alwaies have trade and ſafety, time may come that they may have as much need of friends hereafter, as formerly they had need of us; it is good wiſdome to keep old friends, for ſuch friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is not eaſily found; however they have proſpered, all have not done ſo, and though we know that want makes a man wiſe, yet I never heard of that deſire, that had want for it's object. There is a poſſibility of wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting proviſions for ſhipping, when only by trade it is to be obtained from other Countries, there is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty we may be provided for by our own at home,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:115804:25"/>
it is good to chuſe the ſureſt way. I wiſh that <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New-England</hi> may proſper together; but ſure I am, if the Timber in <hi>New-England</hi> be once waſted neere the Sea ſide, it will be more hard for them to bring it out of the main Land to the Sea, then for <hi>Old-England</hi> that hath it adjoyning to ſome navigable river, if not to the Sea it ſelf. And as for the goodneſſe of it (if we can ſpeak by experience it is well) yet I have not heard of any better then <hi>Old-England</hi> affords. I therefore conclude, and believe it will be moſt ſure and ſafe to preſerve, and improve our owne Native commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
               <p>But in caſe this be not approved of, and all the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Lands muſt be ſold (as ſome do report) then I humbly beg leave to propoſe another way for the preſerving of Timber, which before ſale may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for.</p>
               <p>Firſt, let there be an accompt taken of all the Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, of what kind ſoever, now growing in the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts and Chaces, that are now to be ſold, both quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, quality, and value, in each diviſion of Forreſt and Chace, and let the account be brought to thoſe that ſhall be appointed for the ſale thereof.</p>
               <p>Secondly, then let it be conſidered, how many ſhips are fit to be built, and charged yearly for thirty or forty years, more or leſſe, and if the number of five, ſix, or ſeven, more or leſſe are yearly to be built, the certain number being known, then let the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Navy, or ſome other, ſend unto thoſe which ſhall be appointed for ſale, the ſeverall qualities uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for ſhipping, whether Oak, Aſh, Beech, Elme, Cheſnut, or other wood, and quantity of each quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, proportioning of each quality ſo many load, as in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:115804:25"/>
the whole all ſorts ſhall amount unto the full number of loads which yearly muſt be expended on thoſe ſhips ſo aſcertained to be furniſhed out of the Foreſts and Chaces. Then let thoſe that ſhall be imployed for ſale make the apportionment, and fix it on each Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and Chace ſo much yearly for ſo many years as ſhall be appointed for the ſame; and thus apportion'd, let the purchaſer of thoſe lands give good ſecurity (by his lands) to ſerve in ſo many loads yearly of good ſound &amp; ſerviceable timber at ſuch Wharf or Wharfs as ſhall be firſt agreed upon to be moſt convenient for the building of the foreſaid ſhips; if the State ſhall think fit, this may be (a kind of) a rent charged on the land for ever. If what hath been ſaid be approved of, theſe benefits will enſue, as,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Navy will be conſtantly ſupplied for ſo many years as ſhall be agreed on, without any farther charge to the State.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, the purchaſer will be incouraged (and neceſſitated) to preſerve his young timber, at leaſt ſo ſo much as may inable him to ſerve the proportion that ſhall be ſet upon him by way of Rent.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Purchaſer will be farther incouraged ſo to order his land, that ſome may be for Corn, ſome for Paſture, and ſome for Wood.</p>
               <p>Theſe laſt Propoſalls I thought good here humbly to preſent, not that I like them beſt, but leſt the other ſhould be diſliked. For ſurely in theſe weighty buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes the ſafeſt way is the beſt way.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:115804:26"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:115804:26"/>
            <head>AN APPENDIX, SHEWING The chiefe cauſe of wandring poor in <hi>England,</hi> and the remedies therof.</head>
            <p>THe two great Nurſeries of Idleneſſe and Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery &amp;c. in the Nation, are Ale-houſes, and Commons. The truth of the firſt is ſeen by moſt, and the hurtfull waſt that is to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth thereby is ſuch, that it amounteth to more yearly then any Aſſeſſement for one year, within theſe ten years laſt paſt; and yet the moderate uſe of the creature, whether reſpect be had to neceſſity or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, not to be brought into this accompt.</p>
            <p>If there were an exact accompt of all that ſell Ale or Beer in <hi>England,</hi> there would be found an hundred thouſand. And that you may have ſome little to direct you, take here what hath been done in and about <hi>London,</hi> for the knowledge thereof in the yeare 1646. There were then ſome honeſt men in each Pariſh within the Precincts of the <hi>Militia</hi> of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> did bring in the number of all the houſes that ſold Ale or Beer in each Pariſh, and by conference with ſome of the ableſt to judge in the Tower <hi>Hamblets, Southwark,</hi> and the City of <hi>London,</hi> it was judged that there were not then leſſe then ſix thouſand within the weekly
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:115804:27"/>
Bills of Mortality; ſince that, we have little cauſe to believe their decreaſe.</p>
            <p>And in my obſervation, upon conference with knowing men of moſt Counties of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe eyes have been upon this great evill, it may be belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that there are not leſſe than two hundred thouſand in <hi>England.</hi> But leſt there ſhould be any miſtake in the greater number, I will make uſe of the leſſe, which is one hundred thouſand, to meaſure our waſt, or loſſe by.</p>
            <p>And that this may be more than probable <hi>(viz.)</hi> that there is no leſſe than one hundred thouſand houſes, in which Ale and Beer is ſold within this Nation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I thus compute it.</p>
            <p>The Cities in <hi>England</hi> are twenty and ſix.</p>
            <p>The Market Townes in <hi>England</hi> are ſix hundred and forty.</p>
            <p>The Pariſhes in <hi>England,</hi> (beſides what are in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Market Townes) are eight thouſand at leaſt.</p>
            <p>The Cities (ſay I) have in them, one with another, five hundred, in all thirteen thouſand.</p>
            <p>The Market Townes I judge to have in them, one with another, ſeventy five, in all forty ſeven thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand.</p>
            <p>The Pariſhes one with another have five, in all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thouſand, ſo then if this accompt be allowed, the totall will be one hundred thouſand.</p>
            <p>Having this ſmall meaſure to judge by, which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve is as ſmall as any meaſure they ſell their Ale by, (comparatively) let it be either the ſtreight laced flaggon, or the narrow bottom'd
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:115804:27"/>
pot, the beſt of them is but the one half it ſhould be, and I believe this is the like; but however the wiſe will eaſily judge of the greater, by this leſſe.</p>
            <p>I believe there is no man that looks on the many houſes that ſell Ale or Beer, but will ſay there are too many by the one half, and that what is ſpent in ſuch houſes, is too much by three parts of four, nay many will ſay by nine parts in ten, (in this I agree) but I will take the thoughts of them that judge the leaſt, and ſo take but the one halfe of what is ſpent in theſe hundred thouſand Alehouſes to be a waſt, and allow the other halfe to go for what is of neceſſity, conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, and lawfull delight; for it cannot be denied, but the calling of it ſelf is both lawfull and neceſſary. And our Innes on great roads in <hi>England,</hi> are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly very uſefull, but their entertainment ſuch, that they are an honor to our Nation; and therefore they and ſuch Alehouſes as are conveniently placed for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing of the poor Traveller, ought to have all due incouragement.</p>
            <p>My endeavour here, is only to ſhew the abuſe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by the multitude of unneceſſary Alehouſes, which if conſidered, will be found a great waſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. I will take the leaſt to number by, and be it granted, that there are but an hundred thouſand hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that ſell Ale and Beer (beſides Tavernes, another waſt, which if conſidered, would be found to be a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great impediment to common good, but with them at this time I will not meddle) and what is ſpent in them, the one halfe ſhall be looked upon as waſt, which every drunkard in a ſober fit will allow. Now then grant but this, that each Alehouſe one
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:115804:28"/>
with another, doth ſell but two barrells weekly, in this I take the leaſt, and that each barrell hath three buſhells of Barley Malt, and each buſhell worth three ſhillings and four pence, and this be the charge before it come to be ſold for two pence the flaggon, then there is ſpent in each Alehouſe weekly twenty ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, of which the waſt is ten ſhillings, ſo the waſt in the hundred thouſand Alehouſes weekly is fifty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds, which yearly amounteth to twenty ſix hundred thouſand pounds.</p>
            <p>Here note, I reckon not as it is ſold at two pence the flaggon, for then it would come to neere three times this ſum, nor yet the many hands that are unneceſſarily imployed about this work, as the Husbandman, the Maltſter the Brewer, the Victualler, or Ale-ſeller, all which would find out better imployment for the good of the Common-wealth, if it were no other then to ſit ſpinning, or knitting of Nets for fiſhing, but if they all ſate down idlely, and had no imployment, yet then it would be leſſe hurtfull to the Common-wealth, then ſo imployed as to maintaine drunkenneſſe and beggery.</p>
            <p>I think it needleſſe here to ſpeak of thoſe that I have obſerved to come to beggery, by frequenting of Ale-houſes, if it ſhould reach to hundreds, what would that be to the many thouſand in <hi>England,</hi> that fall to beggery yearly by this great evill!</p>
            <p>Should I begin with Gentlemen of very good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, who make it their only buſineſſe to ſit piping and potting all the day, nay all the week, the yeer, nay their life; and when their eſtate will not bear the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern, or Inns in Townes, yet they may be found in ſome ſmoakie blind Ale-houſe, if it be no more then a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:115804:28"/>
Cott of turfe ſet againſt a tree on ſome Common. And how often is it ſeen that they take their children, yea their eldeſt ſon along with them, and think it well to be the beſt in the company, though it be but with Raddle-men, Tinkers, and Grate-carriers; (ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them alſo hereby to ſpend their time and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect their markets) and ſo this Gentleman by miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpending his eſtate, brings his family, his (it may be) carefull) wife and many children to utter beggery.</p>
            <p>There are very few, but by their own obſervation may more fully demonſtrate the miſery, that ſuch poor ſoules have been brought unto; and who can think of it without grief, to ſee ſo many good parts thus drown'd in an Ale-houſe? And who doth not ſee the Country-Husbandman (in whoſe labour conſiſts the welfare of a Commonwealth) ſpend more time in theſe peſtilent Ale-houſes then he doth on the plough, and oft times runs ſo far on the ſcore, that he runs himſelf out of all, and then he, his wife and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren muſt beg. Do but look on the Tradeſmen, if ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them do not ſpend more time in the Ale-houſe then in their ſhops; and if a Cuſtomer come to ſpeak with him, his carefull wife many times muſt hunt from Ale-houſe to Ale-houſe for her husband, (and many times finds him ſpeechleſſe,) and when he ſhould bee carefully tending that which ſhould keep him, he is careleſly at the Ale-houſe ſpending, and ſo haſtens to beggery himſelf and whole family.</p>
            <p>Look alſo on the poor Labourer (that indeed labors to bring his wife and children to beggery, whether Carpenter, Maſon, or ſuch like) who oftentimes on a Munday-morning going to work, are caught in an Ale-houſe, (which are placed in the way as it were on
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:115804:29"/>
purpoſe) which like Spiders webs, do catch daily ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe ſilly creatures, who oftentimes run more on the ſcore, before they come thence, then they get all the reſt of the week with their labour; and if they miſſe this web the beginning of the week, yet at the later end when they have got a little money, they ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome eſcape, but there ſit drinking themſelves penni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, witleſſe, and their wives and children bloudleſſe; for indeed it is very often ſeen, that they lie languiſhing at home, expecting ſome refreſhing on the Saturday night, when he (like a ravenous creature) lieth ſucking their blood at the Ale-houſe.</p>
            <p>I may inſtance in many more, but ſurely it's enough to mind all men of what daily experience ſpeaks, <hi>viz.</hi> that the multitude of Ale-houſes is the greateſt occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the multitude of beggers in England.</p>
            <p>I cannot imagine a greater waſt in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth then theſe Ale-houſes are an occaſion of: Should I tell you of thirty thouſand buſhells of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley daily in England thrown upon the dunghill, it would not be ſuch a waſt; for that would fat the earth again. Should I tell you of an hundred and twenty thouſand dozen of bread fetcht by a company of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked lewd men from ſeverall Bakers ſhops, purpoſely to ſtarve the poor of this Nation, and throw one dozen in one ſtreet, and another in another; and ſo ſtrew all the ſtreets of England, till all were thrown away, and this done day by day throughout the yeer, ſurely you would cry out on the Magiſtrates, and ſay they were not worthy to live that ſuffer ſuch waſt, as to the ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of ſo many thouſands; yet this bad, is not ſo bad as the great waſte occaſioned by the multitude of Ale-houſes, for this bread ſo thrown away will find
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:115804:29"/>
ſome hogs or dogs to gather it up, which at the worſt would be a preſerving of ſome creature uſefull; but the other ſerves for nothing, but to make men worſe then dogs or hogs, that drink the fruit of many mens labour, and wallow in their own dung: Nay let me ſay, that if lewd wicked men ſhould take thirty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand buſhells of wheat, and throw ſo much daily into ſeverall rivers in England, it would not be ſo deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to the well-being of this Nation, as is the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Ale-houſes that are in this Land at this day; for in the firſt waſt there would be a ſaving of a great labour that goeth to the fitting of it for uſe, which the other takes up before it coms to the drunkard; for it muſt have the Maltſter, the Market, the Mill; beſides many hedges muſt be torn by the Ale-ſeller to brew withall, to the hurt of many mens Corn, which many times is more then all the Malt is worth, which the wretched Ale-man never careth for.</p>
            <p>And what coms of the one half of the drink that is thus ſpent, but to be excremented againſt the wall, and ſo run down the channell, never do more good, till it come to the Sea: and when drunkards drink five do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen in a day, to the loſſe of the Commonwealth, the ſpending of time, and the waſting of his brain and ſpirits, and then comes abroad vomiting and caſting forth ſome at one corner of a ſtreet, ſome at another; at laſt the dirty wretch tumbles himſelf with the reſt in the dirty channells; yet there is no complaining a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Magiſtrate, (the ſaddeſt complaint of all) for the cuſtome in this hath made it genuine to us; ſo that our waſt is inſenſible, though this will (if well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered) bee far greater then any of the other here ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:115804:30"/>
The other great occaſion of our wandring idle beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, is our Commons; for there poor men, that happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly themſelves are honeſt labourers, yet their children are brought up to idleneſſe, having nothing to doe but to tear hedges, or ſome other the like pilfering im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment; and when the father dieth, who during life did get them bread, they are altogether unfit for work, and then beg they muſt.</p>
            <p>There are many Commons in <hi>England,</hi> that have many hundred of ſuch Families living on them (in this the Commons in <hi>England</hi> are fruitfull, for they ſend forth yearly many thouſand idle wandring beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, which have not done a daies work (to the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the Common-wealth) in their lives; for indeed if they have not attained to the uſe of labour in their youth, they ſeldome ever betake themſelves to it when of riper years.</p>
            <p>The remedies will be in taking away the occaſion, and in putting oportunities of being rich into their hand, whereby they may be incouraged to labour: but if neither of theſe will do, then the means muſt be conſtraint.</p>
            <p>The firſt and greateſt remedy will be the ſuppreſſing of many thouſand Alehouſes in <hi>England,</hi> and that by apportioning a certain number to each County (a ſmall number will ſerve, unleſſe on Roads and Market Townes) not to be exceeded upon a great penalty to be on the Juſtices of Peace for every Alehouſe licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed above the number appointed to that County; all Alehouſes to be licenſed at a Quarter Seſſions, and not otherwiſe, and there to be regiſtred, that ſo they may be ſure to keep within the number; and let there be Certificate ſent to the chiefe Officer in every Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:115804:30"/>
of the number and the names of all ſuch that ſhall be licenſed in the ſaid Pariſh. If any ſell without ſuch licenſe, or leſſe then meaſure in any Pariſh, after no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice given to the chiefe Officer, he neglecting to afflict the puniſhment which ſhall be appointed for ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, ſhall have a penalty laid on him, the one half to go to the informer, the other to the poor of the ſame Pariſh: And let the informer have the third pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of all fines that ſhall be ſet on Alefellers, Tiplers, or Gameſters.</p>
            <p>A ſecond remedy will be incloſing of Commons, that ſo there be no room left for idleneſſe; and that thoſe now Cottagers may have ſuch a competent mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of land laid to their Cottages, that may invite their children to labor.</p>
            <p>A third remedy is the erecting of workhouſes and ſetting up ſuch a manufactory that may invite to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, not by force, but where you meet with reſolute idle perſons, ſuch conſtrain to the mill, or ſome other hard labour; then he that will not work, let him not eat; mans nature is more eaſily drawn, then driven. I have often ſeen in and about <hi>London</hi> Porters take up ſuch burthens for the rewards ſake, that would have broke a good horſes back, and poor men that carry ſacks of coals from the water ſide, that make their knees to buckle, and their backs to bend, and theſe vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily taken up for the pays ſake, is done with much willingneſſe; but if halfe that weight ſhould have been forced on them by authority, they would have fallen down under it, crying out upon oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and cruelty, as not poſſible to be undergone; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my advice is that ſuch works be found out, and ſuch wages given that may invite them to a willing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:115804:31"/>
If in theſe workhouſes they earne but half their livelihood, it will be a great ſaving to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, as I have already ſhowne in Section the ninth. And I believe, if they were but for ſome time unwonted of their idle courſe, they would then be quickly aſhamed of it, and as well find out imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment themſelves, as the poor in the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other place do.</p>
            <p>The ſeverall wayes of imployment were too long here to inſiſt on, and ſhould I come to particulars (fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for a debate then a pen) yet there muſt be a large la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude ſtill left to the wiſdome of thoſe that ſhall be intruſted in the ordering of this affaire: For reſpect herein muſt be had to each commodity of an Engliſh producture, and that what of that is tranſported doe not procure an over-balance, and ſo that be ſaid of us on this account, what was ſaid on another by a great maſter in humane affaires, to wit, that <hi>England</hi> is a great Animal, and not to be deſtroyed, but by it ſelfe.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Prov. 27. 23, 24, 25.</bibl>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Be thou diligent to know the ſtate of thy flocks, and look well to thy herds.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thy hay appeareth, and the tender graſſe ſheweth it ſelf, and herbs of the mountains are gathered.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The lambs are for thy cloathing, and the goats are the price of thy field.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And thou ſhalt have goats milk enough for thy food, for the food of thy houſhold, and for maintenance of thy maidens.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
